<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Release notes</title>
    <author email="jahlborn@users.sf.net">James Ahlborn</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="1.1.1" date="2007-10-10">
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        Incorporated code review changes before open sourcing.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.0" date="2007-08-02">
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        Added corba example for the new custom RPC exporter functionality.
      </action>
      <action dev="mdelaurentis" type="add">
        Add LineIterator, an iterator over lines read from a BufferedReader.
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        Add the RemoteStreamExporter and associated classes which allow the
        stream servers to be easily utilized within alternative RPC
        frameworks.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.5" date="2007-07-18">
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        Added convenience IOIterator implementation ConverterIOIterator which
        is useful for implementing IOIterators which convert from one data
        type to another.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.4" date="2007-6-6">
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="update">
        Add ability to specify chunk size for the underlying streams in remote
        iterator servers
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="update">
        Change RemoteRetry to catch and potentially retry any exception.
        Change current concrete retry impls to only handle RemoteException (so
        their behavior will be the same as it was before).  Do not throw
        RemoteException by default from call() methods.  These changes make
        RemoteRetry friendlier for use with ejb3 stuff.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.3" date="2007-05-17">
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="update">
        add Proxy support to RemoteWrapper for simplified usage.
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        deprecate (Closeable)IOIterator.Adapter and add RmiioUtil.adapt method
        which returns a subclass of AbstractCloseableIOIterator (which will
        close the underlying iterator if it is Closeable).
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="update">
        make IOIteratorPipe.Source extend RemoteStreamMonitor so that it will
        get automagically closed if used with a SerialRemoteIteratorServer.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.2" date="2007-02-16">
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        Added example code.
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        Added CloseableIOIterator convenience interface.  Made all IOIterator
        and Closeable implementations implement this interface instead.  Added
        AbstractCloseableIOIterator which implements closing using a variety
        of common mechanisms.
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="update">
        Move some utility classes into a utility sub-package.
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="update">
        Add noDelay functionality to PacketInputStream.  Change implementation
        of EncodingInputStream to make it more effective in noDelay mode.  Add
        addtional constructors to encoding based iterators to allow for
        noDelay remote iterators.
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="update">
        Change SerialRemoteIteratorServer to attempt to use localIterator as
        the stream monitor if none is explicitly provided and the
        localIterator implements the relevant interface.
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        InputStreamAdapter and OutputStreamAdapter for customizing stream
        handling based on whether or not the underlying stream is packet
        based.
      </action>
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        Add SimpleRemoteIterator, which is implementation of RemoteIterator
        suitable for small collections.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0.1" date="2006-10-17">
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        Make IOIterator.Adapter more flexible
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="1.0" date="2006-09-06">
      <action dev="jahlborn" type="add">
        Initial release as separate rmiio project.
      </action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
